Let's do exactly the same demonstration,
but this time for a class C end-device.
Whatever the device and network Server, if
you want to set up a class C LoRaWAN
transmission, we have to : First register
a class C end-device
on the Network Server.
In my case, I'm still with my class A end
device, so I just need to
switch from class A to class C.
Secondly, we have to configure the end
device as a class C, on the device itself.
Okay, so let's do this.
I set up exactly the same environment with
once again my device log on the left
and on the right two tabs.
The first tab is the gateway log and
the second tab is my application.
As I said, I'm still with my class
A end device called device1-OTAA.
So I need to change its class. On the
network server used for
this demonstration.
I can do that in general settings.
Go down to network layer section and we
can find the LoRaWAN class capabilities.
Keep in mind that even if the procedure is
different on the network server you use,
if your LoRaWAN server supports class C,
then you just have to find where in the
user interface you can
change this parameter.
On the device side, it was a class A
end device for the last demonstration.
So I just have to change class A
to class C in the config file.
Then I compile and program my end device.
And now we're ready.
I can now power up my end device
and the Join procedure starts.
Once again,
when the join procedure is completed, the
device application waits for the user to
press the push button to send a
temperature through the lower network.
However, at this point there is one last
requirement before using
class C capabilities.
Because, we could think that if I send a
downlink from the network right now,
it would arrive to the end device.
Actually, this is not
true, at least not yet.
Because the specification says that the
device must validate its
activation to the network server.
What does it mean?
It means that the network server wants to
be sure that the device has finished its
activation and is running a valid session.
Doing that is very easy.
It only has to send one
uplink and that's okay.
This activation validation is just a way
to prevent the network server to send down
link data to a device for which
the join procedure has failed.
Because in that case, all
downlink would be useless.
The downlink transmission on a gateway is
shared between all LoRaWAN device, so it's
very limited and there is no need to
waste it with useless transmission.
So I launched an uplink with the push
button and I can check that everything
has been transmitted to my application.
So now the network server knows
that my device has a valid session.
Great.
Now I go back to the downlink messaging
tool, messaging tab and downlink.
Let's choose again
Fport equal 20 and AA for the payload.
Then I hit the schedule downlink button.
As soon as I hit the button, then the
message goes all the way to my gateway
and IoT is received on my end device.
And I didn't have to send
any uplink frame for that.
I can also see that this packet has
been received in the Class C time slot.
This time slot is actually the time
between two uplinks where the radio has
been kept power up to receive data, so
I can send as many downlinks as I want.
The only restriction you have is the
regional reglementation, for example
the 1%  duty-cycle on the 868 MHz band.
And there can also be some restriction
depending on the subscription you have
with your network server operator.
For example, they can limit the number of
downlink, or they can charge
you an extra fee for this.